All right, so hello, guys,
and welcome back to CS25.
Today, I'm a very glad
to welcome Victoria
Lin from Thinking Machines Lab.
So she's a member
of technical staff
there, where she focuses on
native multimodal intelligence.
And she is passionate about
building AI systems that
empower humans to tackle
complex, knowledge-intensive
problems effectively.
And previously, she was
a research scientist
at Meta AI and
Salesforce AI Research.
And she received her PhD from
the University of Washington.
And without further ado,
let's give it up for Victoria.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you for having me.
So can you hear me OK?
Yeah, so I'm very
glad to be here
today and talk about native
multimodal language models.
So a declaration is this talk is
going to be exclusively focused
on public materials.
And the talk represents my own
opinion, not of my employer.
So without further
ado, let's start it.
So I think without
much argument,
large language models is one of
the most exciting breakthrough
happened in the past few years.
I think nowadays, probably
everyone sitting in this room
will use language
models a little bit,
like during your daily life.
So for example, like asking
questions through ChatGPT,
using Cloud Code, or Codex to
help you to code your project.
So these models were built
based on next token prediction
over symbolic information.
And they scale to demonstrate
amazing emergent capabilities.
So just as a quick recap.
How does today's large
language model paradigms works?
So here's architecture.
You will be familiar with it.
This is a transformer cell.
So basically, it carries
out next token prediction.
Predict the probability
distributed over a vocabulary.
And we train such a model
using a large number of corpus
curated over different domains.
And as we noticed that as
the data and model scales,
they start to demonstrate
amazing capabilities such
as they can acquire a
large amount of knowledge.
They can be post-trained
to follow instructions.
And they are able to carry out
a train of thought reasoning.
And most recently, we also
found they are actually
able to plan to solve
complicated tasks.
However, I'm also going to argue
that just the language modeling
alone is not enough for us.
So why is it?
It is because both the digital
world we deal with every day
and also the physical
world we live in,
they are actually filled
with information coming
from different modalities.
Like images, audio, video.
So if you surf on
the internet, you
will get what I'm talking about.
And also, suppose if we're
building AI systems that's
going to interact with us real
time in the physical world,
we have to deal with
multimodal information.
So the goal is to
build basically
AI systems that's not only
processing symbolic knowledge,
but it's also able
to seamlessly handle
these multimodal
information sharing to us,
in terms of visual and
auditory information.
And actually, if
you pay attention
to today's state of the art
language model landscape,
you will see, for a lot of
recent models being rolled out,
they have already been claiming
that these models are native,
multimodal, and
are able to process
large amount of multimodal
information, which is true.
We see very amazing
capabilities from these models
in terms of image,
video understanding,
visual genetic
coding, and so on.
So the first part
of this talk is just
going to dive into the building
philosophies of such models.
So what do we define as native
multimodal language models?
I myself personally
find it easier
to understand this
paradigm by thinking
with an analogy of
language models.
So the state of the art
multimodal language model
architecture is really
performing tokenization
across the board, which means
whether the incoming information
comes as image modality,
video modality,
or is a piece of audio,
we try to find a way
to convert these signals into
token information that can be
processed by the transformer.
And on top of that, we perform
global autoregressive generation
modeling similar
to language models.
So exactly what do I mean?
So for text, we
can tokenize them
similar as what we do for
large language models.
Usually, we can use
byte pair encoding.
Break down the text into
small pieces of tokens.
And for images, turns out we
can also do similar things.
So when a whole piece
of image coming in,
we can perform an operation
which we call the patchify.
So basically, we can divide
this image into small parts.
And parts is usually predefined
by a standard size, such as 16
pixels times 16 pixels.
So once we standardize the image
units, we can run, for example,
encoders on these
image units and get
vector representations of them.
And then we sequentialize
these vectorization
of the image units, and then
we got the image tokens.
For audio, we can perform
similar operation.
When the waveform comes in,
we can perform transforms
on top of the waveform.
And we can apply certain
operations basically
to tokenize the
resulting representation.
And accordingly, you can encode
your audio tokens as well.
And for videos.
So this slide is dense.
But what really is
saying is for videos,
we can also easily seen them
as a sequence of images.
So if we think of a video
segment as a sequence of image,
we can perform a
similar petrification
on each of the video frame.
And then we
concatenate the patches
of all the images in
this video sequence,
and then we can still
represent the video
as a sequence of tokens.
So when I say tokens, they are
not necessarily discrete tokens.
If we encode them
into a dense vector,
we still refer to
them as tokens.
And basically, we perform this
tokenization across a board.
And then we can basically
getting multimodal information
sequence.
We can train them
in the same way
as we train a large
language model.
So for state of the art
multimodal language models,
when we speak of
them, usually there
are two broad types of them.
So one type of multimodal
models consider multimodality
as input, but only text
modality as output.
So as is shown here, so we have
a multimodal sequence coming in.
We condition them, but we
only calculate the losses
on the text tokens.
So this can induce amazing
understanding abilities.
Like we have an image as
input, video as input.
The model can start to
answer questions in text.
And in fact, lots of
multimodal language models,
you are probably
familiarized today
like Gemini, Qwen, and Kimi,
they operate in this mode.
So which means it's multimodal
input and text only output.
Of course, I think these
companies have also
developed other models
which is able to generate
multimodal information.
But a lot of the core products
is doing text only output.
So there is another
categories of models, which
is called the Omni models.
So which means they not only
take multimodal information
as input, but they also
do multimodal information
as output.
In this case, these models,
is capable of generating
not only text, but
also images and audios.
So something like you might be
familiar with GPT-4 0, which
is named Omni, because it
can also generate images.
So this is an important
slide for today,
because I think this summarized
that by taking this tokenization
view, how we could transfer
a lot of the architecture
and training principles from the
large language modeling paradigm
to the multimodal paradigm.
So there are a couple of
benefits we can get from it.
So first, by designing
such architectures,
this allows us to build
multimodal models, which
is able to allow us to conduct
prompting and instruction
following.
So we can prompt these models
with mixed model prompts
and and enable them to solve
complicated tasks which
requires multimodality.
This model will also acquire
planning and reasoning
capabilities.
And now, even more
amazingly, they
can plan and reason with
multimodal information.
So another exciting
thing is we also
observed that some positive
learnings from large language
modeling, including scaling
data and model size, that
can lead to performance
improvement,
can also be transferred
to multimodal.
Which means for these models,
we see significant promise
that if we further scale up the
number of parameters in them
and also we scale up
the training database,
their performance is going
to get better and better,
and we're going to see
more emergent capabilities.
So the only interesting
remaining here
is I think unlike text modeling,
which has very accurate scaling
laws.
So basically people is able to
derive the power law equation
and fit the coefficients
of the equation,
I think the exact scaling
law study for multimodal
is underexplored.
But on a rough trend,
we are still seeing
this scaling capability.
So I think, for
example, trying to find
the exact fit of
multimodal scaling
law could be a very interesting
future research topic.
The force is a lot of
architectural scaling techniques
and also efficient
techniques, such as mixture
of experts and
these variations, we
can also apply them directly
to multimodal language models
to achieve better
scaling performance.
So next, I basically
want to talk
about the second category
of multimodal models, which
are the Omni models.
Because my past
research group has
been dedicated to
developing such models,
and I want to present a
few variations of these.
So when we come to Omni models,
because they can generate
not only text modality.
So there are a few key
research questions.
So the first one is, how do
we enable them to generate
the non-text modalities?
And the second is, is
there a possible transfer
between understanding
and generation
of the non-text modalities?
So with these questions
in mind, the first model
I'm going to talk about
is the Chameleon family.
So these models adopt a
very simple hypothesis.
So basically, the
question to ask
is, can we actually
simply tokenize
every modality, converting
them into discrete tokens?
This is a very powerful view.
If it is successful,
basically, it
will allow us to model
the multimodal world
as a sequence of
discrete tokens,
so that lots of properties
of language models
could potentially transfer.
So this is basically
the hypothesis
with the Chameleon models.
And the key here is, how
do we discretize images?
And it turns out, it's
not that difficult.
So remember the patchified
view we just talked about.
So for Chameleon,
basically we just
apply another step of
vectorization of these image
patches.
So how do we do that
is given an image,
we convert them into patches.
And then basically, we
run a continuous encoders
on top of them to get the
embeddings of these patches.
And once we get these
patches, we don't stop there.
We follow it up with a
learned vector codebook.
Then basically, we can take
our computed embeddings
and try to match
them with a codebook,
basically to get to the closest
discrete correspondence of each
of the patches.
And by this way, basically,
we can convert an image
into a sequence of
discrete representation.
And that's how we
tokenize the image, which
is really by finding
their corresponding index
in the codebook.
So basically, we
discretize the images
using the VQ-VAE technique.
And then we put the
image and text together
as an interleaved sequence.
And then basically, we apply
cross-entropy language model
training objective on this.
So the result of
Chameleon model, basically
found that it is able to
generate interleaved text
and image in arbitrary order.
So here, I'm showing a sequence
of image and text generated
by this model.
So basically, you can
see we can actually
generate mixed model documents
from this model directly.
And with this
representation, it will also
allow us to perform
multitasking similar as how
we do with our language models.
So basically, we can give these
models mixed model prompts
and get output from it,
such as we can chat with it,
do brainstorming, compare
images, and so on.
So this is a model
that purely trying
to apply the large language
model technique to mixed model
modeling.
So it is one of the
first model to show
that if we train from scratch
interleaved text and image
sequences, it can induce
multimodal capabilities
while preserving the strong
text only performance.
However, we also
realize some limitations
when we discretize the image.
So basically, one is for
image understanding tasks,
discretization often cause
significant information loss.
So as a result,
when we compare it
to the state of the
art multimodal language
models nowadays, which is
running a continuous image
encoding such as
SigLIP, there is usually
a significant performance gap
in terms of image understanding.
And the second is even
on the generative side,
we also found that basically
discretizing the images
and generate them actually
poses some challenges in terms
of token efficiency.
So these models, which
means these models typically
needs to be trained on
large amounts of data
to be able to sample
well-formed images.
So in summary, Chameleon
presented a very interesting
paradigm where we can train
text and images interleaved
from scratch.
But we also found
the limitations.
Basically the assumption that
we can discretize information
in the images might
be too strong.
So transfusion is
another approach,
which is proposed in roughly
the similar time as Chameleon.
So which basically tries
to actually overcome
some of the limitations
of Chameleon.
So transfusion is a very
interesting and also impactful
architecture.
So basically, it tries to
adopt continuous representation
of the images,
using them as input,
but also tries to
directly predict
these continuous
representation of images.
So how do we predict continuous
representation of images?
So if you are familiar with
diffusion models, so basically,
diffusion models is a
very successful approach
for image generation.
And it conducts image generation
by starting from a noise,
and continuously
predict the noise
to be removed from
this initial noise
until you arrived
at a clear picture.
So basically what
transcription does
is it combines autoregressive
language modeling
and diffusion based
image generation
in a single transformer.
So the input to a
transfusion model
is still an interleaved
text and image sequence.
And for the text, we perform
standard autoregressive
modeling.
But for the image part, instead
of autoregressive prediction,
we take a segment of
image representation
and basically try to do
diffusion operation on it.
The model can perform
multiple step of diffusion.
Get the clear image and then
take the clear image as input
and move autoregressively.
So some important architectural
changes related is for text,
we can continue to use this
causal attention structure.
And for the images, for the
sake of better performance,
we apply bidirectional attention
on top of these images.
So this is the
transformation architecture.
So basically as shown in
the transfusion paper,
so these models is able
to quickly generate
much better image
quality compared
to discrete token-based
image generation using
much less token budget.
So in summary, so transformation
is a first approach,
which seamlessly
unify autoregressive
next token prediction and
the diffusion objective
for multimodal modeling.
It demonstrates a significant
better image generation quality
and token efficiency.
On the other hand, there is
also open research problem.
Because for the
transfusion paper,
it is still trying
to represent--
it is still trying to represent
multimodal information
in text and image
interleaved sequences.
However, it adopts
the VAE representation
for the images, which is
very efficient for generating
the images.
But on the other
hand, these are not
very efficient representation
for image understanding tasks.
So this creates a dilemma.
So which is still
an open problem,
I would say, in the
research field today.
Basically, the field found
that for image generation
and understanding, we sometimes
need two types of encodings
for them.
So state of the art
models today often
tries to overcome this
shortcoming by adopting
two types of image encodings.
Cool.
So we talk about two
types of Omni models,
like using different
representation
for the image modality.
So what else can we further
innovate on this architecture
to basically to make
them more efficient?
So next, I'm going to talk
about a technique which
modifies the transformer
backbone architecture.
So basically, the
motivation comes from that.
Now we are having the
transformers process multimodal
information.
However different modalities
have different information
density.
The nature of the data
is also very different
when it comes to text
and images, for example.
So the question
is, is it necessary
that we have to use
unified transformer
parameters to process
these modalities,
or can we actually introduce
something specialized
to each modality?
So this basically takes us to
an architecture which we call
the mixture of transformers.
So basically, the idea behind
the mixture of transformers
is we try to come up with
independent set of transformer
parameters for each
of the modalities.
So by independent
set of parameters,
I'm referring to such as
[INAUDIBLE] projection matrices
in the attention layer, as
well as the feed forward layer.
So basically, we have
an independent set
of parameters for transformer
parameters for each
of the modality.
For the text modality,
as shown here,
given an input sequence
with interleaved modalities,
we basically select to
activate the set of parameters
based on the modality
deterministically.
If it is a text
token, we activate
the text set of parameters.
If it is an image token, we
activate the image parameters.
If it's the audio token, we
activate the speech parameters.
So as shown here, we performed
this in the attention layer.
Once we get the QKV
projection separately,
we perform a joint attention
over these modality
tokens to allow them to unify.
Once we get the unified output
from the attention layer,
we pass them through
the feedforward layer.
And the feedforward layer here,
again, is divided by modality.
So each modality will have its
own feedforward parameters.
And once we pass these tokens
through the feedforward layer,
we get the normal
transformer output.
So basically from
the outside, we still
have a transformer unit.
We get the token
input and output.
But on the inside, the
processing for each modality
happens differently, using
different set of parameters.
And this technique
can basically can
be combined by with
the two models I just
talked about with the
Chameleon models, which is,
using autoregressive
cross-entropy objective for each
of the modality tokens.
Or with the
transformation technique,
which is using autoregressive
objective for text
and the diffusion
objective for images.
So I'm going to show some
experiments we conducted
with this architecture.
So basically, we did a
scaling ladder for this one.
And we scanned them.
We trained them for
different model sizes.
Like from the smallest, which
is 163 million parameters,
to the largest, which is
seven billion parameters.
So we always compare them with
basically the dense baseline.
And notice that if we
directly compare it
with a dense baseline,
basically mixture transformers
will have an advantage, because
it has double the parameters.
So we also compared with a
baseline which is basically
a mixture of expert model.
So which has roughly
the same amount
of total parameters
as the MoT model.
So here are some results.
So basically, we show
the training loss.
And also the validation on
the image modality generation.
So we show the validation loss.
We also show some
basically sampling
based image generation
evaluation metrics.
So one thing we found is that
the mixture of the transformer
technique is especially
effective at improve
the generation of
non-text modalities.
So here, I didn't show the
text modality generation.
You can refer to the paper.
But in the paper, we found
that actually MoT architecture
will demonstrate similar
comparable text performance
as a dense variation.
So what it really shines it is
able to, without sacrificing
the text performance, achieving
much better performance,
generating non-text
modalities such as images,
as is shown here.
So here, you can
see the right curve,
basically MoT will have a much
lower image generation loss.
And also on the
sample evaluation,
it will show much better
performance compared
to the dense variation.
So an explanation for this is
non-text modality generation
is probably something unique
compared to text generation.
So if we put everything
inside a single transformer,
there might be severe
capacity computation.
But if we can allow
these separate abilities
with different
set of parameters,
we are able to scale
them much better.
So here are some
qualitative results.
So basically, we show that
so for the top line, which
is the dense baseline,
and the bottom line
is like the mixture of
transformer architecture
for image generation.
So basically, we found
that across many examples,
the MoT architecture
is basically able
to follow fine-grained
instructions much better
and generate much
detailed objects.
So here is just to mention
that the mixture of transformer
technique can also be combined
with mixture of experts.
So before I was saying
for each of the modality,
we keep one copy of the
transformer parameters.
But we can also use the
mixture of expert technique
to scale them.
So for example, we
can choose to allocate
different amount of experts
to different modalities.
So I think we used to find
that allocating more experts
is especially helpful
for tax performance.
While for abilities such
as image generation,
usually it doesn't
scale as fast as text
when you're adding
the number of experts.
So which motivates us.
We can potentially have
customized number of experts
for different modalities.
Cool.
So to summarize, so
basically the mixture
of transformer technique
I talked about,
it is a technique which employs
modality specific parameters.
And it performs deterministic
routing on the tokens
when passing them
through the transformer.
These techniques, we found it to
be able to substantively improve
generation quality for
non-text modalities,
including image and speech.
And we found that it's
also a technique which
is helpful to enable the overall
stability and controllability
of mixed model
training, because now we
have different set of parameters
for different modalities.
This can actually allow us to
perform asynchronous training
for these modalities.
So a common scenario
people use it
is suppose we have some
off the shelf text models
already been built. It has
very strong text capabilities.
And now we want to add, for
example, image generation
or speech generation
to this model.
So then instead of
performing full fine tuning
or continuous training on this
existing off the shelf language
model, what's possible is to add
an additional set of parameters
for image or speech to it.
And then we can
freeze the text model,
keeping its text
capability unchanged
and just training the image
and speech parameters.
So this basically allows
a simple technique
to extend existing models with
additional modality generation.
Question?
[INAUDIBLE]
--the generation of images
are two different systems.
For example, the text to image
is more like large language
models and image to text is--
no, it's another way around.
It's like image to text is more
like large language models,
and text to image is more
like diffusion models.
But it's multimodality, meaning
that you want to unify these,
having a single model to achieve
the best in both directions.
Is there a loop, image to
text and image and things?
Yes.
So this is a very good question.
So basically, the
question asked about--
so image understanding,
which is more image to text,
versus image generation,
which is more text to images.
They seem to be
different capabilities.
We hear talking about having
a single transformer which
is doing well in terms of both.
So this is a great question.
Actually, it is not.
So here, when I'm
talking, so in the mixture
of transformer context, when
I talk about image modality,
I'm referring to
image generation.
So I think we actually didn't
found modality separation
to help image understanding.
So it seems that
so the capability
is bounded by whether you are
outputting text or outputting
images.
But if you're outputting
text, your input tokens better
go through the same
set of parameters,
whether they are text or images.
Yeah, so that's
a great question.
Yep, so and finally,
just to mention,
since this publication,
so MoT has inspired
a growing line of follow-up work
in modality aware architectures.
So I'm going to quickly
talk a few work done
by other people, which inherited
the MoT modeling architecture.
So the first one I'm
going to talk about
is actually related to
the question just now.
So basically in last, there
was a very strong Omni model
came out named BAGEL.
So BAGEL employed architecture
very closely related to MoT
So basically, they have
separate set of parameters
for image generation.
But on the other
hand, their base model
is actually a multimodal
language model.
So basically, they have a
separate set of parameters
for image generation.
But for the understanding
part, the understanding part
can actually take in
both text and images.
So basically, BAGEL was
using a different set
of encoding representations for
image understanding features.
And also image understanding
and image generation
goes through a separate
set of parameters.
So I think this is also related
to a problem I just mentioned
before, which is the
field haven't yet
found a very effective way.
So there's currently
ongoing research.
But I think right
now, we don't have
a very effective way to
unify image generation
and understanding.
So here, one
interesting capability
shown in the BAGEL
paper is because recall,
we are modeling
mixed model sequences
as an autoregressive generation.
So it unlocks
capabilities such as we
can allow the model to plan
before it generates an image.
So basically, the
model can first
generate thinking tracing
text and then generate
the final image.
So the paper show
that this would
allow the models to generate
images with much better details.
And I think it's also
basically thinking
before generation is
also the technique, which
is used by lots of the state of
the art image generation models
nowadays.
So another type of adoption
for the mixture of transformer
architecture was actually in
the embodied AI community.
So basically, it's very
interesting that we found--
so it wasn't included
in our original paper.
But we actually found
that in robotics actually,
lots of current architectures
will use MoT style architecture
to predict the action vectors.
So basically instead
of generating images,
so for these type of problems,
action is a different modality.
And basically, these
models will adopt
like an extra special set of
parameters for action prediction
using an architecture
very similar to MoT.
So again, basically,
the idea is while it
is having a separate
set of architecture,
the overall language
modeling structure
and the self-attention
in the transformer
will allow the base language
models, world knowledge,
and so on to transform
to the action prediction,
which will make the
prediction much better.
Cool.
So yes.
So here, I actually
also have a special set
of slides dedicated to the
question we just discussed.
So basically their
positive transfer
between understanding and
generation of the non-text
modalities.
So here, I think we need to
see them in two directions.
So basically, in terms
of better understanding
can help generation, the
answer is strongly, yes.
So basically, people
found that if we
build a better understanding
capabilities in the base model,
so this will allow the model
to have much better information
processing ability, planning
ability, reasoning ability.
So it will allow us to
generate images, which are
much more fine grained details.
And for infographics, it
can generate infographics
with more accurate information,
less hallucination.
But on the other hand,
suppose we take Omni model
and we further train them
for generation capabilities
on the non-text modalities.
There has been
little work showing
that this has a positive
transfer for understanding
capability.
So in plain words, which is if
we train the model for image
generation and we train it
on a lot of token budget,
it doesn't necessarily
improve the model's ability
to perform image
understanding tasks.
Which is very interesting.
So I think related is last year.
So basically, the Berkeley
professor Sergey Levine
also tweeted on his account.
Basically, he mentioned that
it is puzzling that we can--
basically, language model can
acquire such amazing abilities
through next token prediction.
But on the other hand, we don't
make video models much stronger
if we do next frame prediction.
So this is a very interesting
phenomena people have observed
and a couple of explanations.
They are a little bit
hand-wavy, which is also like--
some of them is also included
in Sergey's original post.
So one hypothesis is
language is fundamentally
different from the
other modalities,
because it is a highly
compressed abstraction
of human cognition.
So when we are training on
language next token prediction,
we are actually already trained
on basically human's reasoning
process.
And also some of the
words we see also
implies actions we
are going to take.
Versus in comparison,
the images and videos,
they are sensory data.
They are not our subjective
interpretation of the word.
But instead, they are
the passive observation
of the world.
So training on them, we will
have very different consequences
compared if we
train on languages.
And also for image and
videos, the loss landscape
is more complicated.
So there has been some
experiments basically
showing that even when the image
and video generation is not
looking great to humans,
their loss might have already
been starting to look good.
So basically, designing the loss
landscape for images and videos
are also more complicated.
And there's also
other hypotheses.
For example, if we just
look at the real world,
next frame prediction
would be very redundant.
Because there will be lots
of redundant information
and replication
across video frames,
which could possibly
contribute to this.
But I think overall, this is
a very interesting phenomenon
worth bearing in
mind, which could also
point to us that although
we see lots of success,
applying learnings from
large language modeling
to multimodal modeling,
this is likely not the end.
So there is much more
fundamental problems
to solve when it comes
to multimodal models.
Yeah.
So here is basically
a summary slides.
So basically what it
says is the models
I just presented, which
I call Omni language
models, like
Chameleon, transfusion,
mixture of experts,
so they solve
a small subset of the
multimodal intelligence
problems we face today.
So they especially excel
at multimodal information
processing.
But when it comes to
the wild physical world,
when we talk about things like
spatial temporal understanding,
real time understanding,
robotics control,
there are still lots of
unaddressed problems,
and people are still dedicated
to understanding and coming up
with better representations for
these multi-modal information
when you come to real
world processing.
With this, I also want
to conclude my talk.
So basically, I hope
this talk has motivated
that building models with
native multimodal capabilities
is a very active
research field nowadays.
It has a ton of open problems.
It's not as figured
out as language models.
And for today, lots
of multimodal language
models we see, they excel at
digital information processing.
But we still are far
away from a paradigm
which could perform powerful
physical world multimodal
intelligence.
Multimodal models
compare with text models,
they are more
computationally heavy,
which requires additional
challenges to be solved in terms
of training and infrastructure.
And also, multimodal itself is a
very complicated and interesting
problem space.
So like we just mentioned,
digital information
understanding would require
multimodal processing.
Physical intelligence would
require multimodal processing.
Robotics would require
multimodal processing.
So in the short
term, we will likely
see an increasing number of
multimodal models customized
for these certain capabilities.
And how to unify them
into a coherent system,
that will also be a very
interesting future research
paradigm.
So with this, I will
conclude the talk,
and I'm happy to
take more questions.
[APPLAUSE]
All right, great.
We'll be taking questions
in person and online.
I'll go around with the mic.
Hi.
Thank you for coming.
My question is broad,
but more generally,
I think there's certain
information that humans
are able to interpret visually
and other information that we
interpret through words.
So I'm wondering,
when you're coming up
with these architectures or
thinking about these models,
how do you consider
these different streams
and how to actually trade
information between them?
Because if you do have
these mixture of experts,
you're isolating how
they learn their work.
OK, so the question
is, so, for example,
we just presented a
modular architecture,
like mixture of transformers.
And if we isolate
the representation
for different modalities,
how do we still
able to unify the information?
So one thing is
definitely, these models
still have the
self-attention mechanism.
So once we project the different
tokens using their customized
projection, they still go
through self-attention.
So that is one way to allow
information still transfer
across modality.
So I think that's one thing.
And I think the
other way it goes,
basically modeling
still happens is
through this causal
conditioning.
So we still have this structure
of given input as image,
you need to do text prediction.
So even with separate
set of parameters.
So these autoregressive
orders is still there.
So that's why we are still
able to model conditioning
on these text, generate
this image conditioning
on these image generated text.
Yeah.
I have a question.
What are your thoughts
on generative role models
for solving some of the
things you discussed,
like real world interaction,
multimodal learning,
and so forth?
Because one slide,
you mentioned how
language might be an abstraction
of our reasoning or thoughts,
whereas pixels are more dense.
But I think, which Japa,
is that they're trying
to abstract that as well.
Yeah, so I think japa.
Is a very interesting
architecture.
I recall, I think at the
beginning of this series,
we also have a talk on Japa.
So how do I see it is think it
is because multimodal space is
so rich.
So we have different types
of problems to solve.
So we might actually
have the need
for different representations
for different applications.
So nowadays, I
think one thing we
observe is if coming to
infographic understanding,
like PDFs of visual coding.
So it seems like our current
patchify and encoder paradigm
works very well.
But on the other
hand, infographics
is also a very different kind
of image modality compared
to real world, especially
scenarios where it requires
physical spatial understanding.
So I believe Japa, it's
architecture specifically
designed to be more efficient
in terms of modeling
some of these relations.
So I do think it's worth--
basically we should explore
different architectures,
especially when it comes
to these real world
physical understanding.
Yeah, thanks for that response.
Anybody else have a question?
Hi, I'm curious to get your
thoughts on learning more
from these multimodal
models, where maybe there's
extra understanding that
comes from understanding
the world that could transfer
to just general knowledge work
and agent capabilities.
Do you think there is
room for that to happen?
Sorry, would you mind
repeat the question?
Yeah.
Do you think it's
possible that by training
these multimodal
models and Omni models,
they could get better at general
knowledge work, not just at,
for example, generating videos?
But as humans, I think we learn
a lot from the real world.
Do you think there is
room to make models
that can learn from video and
other forms of modality that
make them better at just
knowledge work, though?
Yeah, OK.
I think the question is,
if by training these models
for video generation,
can we make them better
at knowledge work?
So the short answer, as I
just touched a little bit
in the talk, is
so far, we haven't
found it to be very effective
for this type of transfer.
So in terms of we
do video generation
versus transferring
back to knowledge work.
But on the other
hand, I do think
we have more promising
signals now, because I think,
for example, lots of
robotics tasks or training,
it actually requires--
it's being assisted
by some video models, like
for future state prediction,
get feedback, and so on.
So I think there could be a way.
But I think so far, we
are still in a state
where we haven't seen that.
We just train a model
purely for video generation.
And then it got massively
better at a GenAI task.
So for example, like the
video generation capability
is used as a feedback for
how you do the next action
prediction.
Any other interesting questions?
Hello.
I was wondering if you've
done any kind of scaling law
where you turn actual
texts into some kind
of black or white pictures?
Because we do that if you remove
those quantization from VAEs.
The learned tokenization
shouldn't be a problem.
And in fact, if you
have a tiny model that
is conditioned on
text and generate
just an image of that
text, that's also doable.
And so it's just that it's
not totally efficient,
it doesn't work
well and all that.
But is there a scaling law that
says it's like 20 times worse
or something.
Consider that a lot
of the Gemini models
can now solve
Sudoku individually.
So how worse is that?
Is there a crossover
point where you
can achieve that with
just decent engineering
and then remove an
entire modality and just
use text and image this way?
I see.
So basically, I
think the question
is it possible to just
render text as images?
And that gives us a way
to unify the modalities.
Specifically, because now the
VAE seems to be a bottleneck.
And now that we do pixel level
predictions and all that.
And it seems like, yeah, we're
not overly wrongly compressing
images anymore, because VAE
seemed to not have been made
with that particular use case.
Yeah, so I haven't done
such experience myself.
But I do remember seeing a paper
early on coming out this year.
So I think I recall the
paper is about basically
they are training
language models
but just giving images as input.
And they actually got
pretty good results.
So basically, I think
basically then later you
can prompt this model by
showing it to OCR images.
I think we should all
check out our paper,
whether it has efficiency
or the scaling loss study.
So how efficient is.
My prediction.
Is it will be less
efficient compared
if we train on raw text.
I think just because I
think texts already have
this nice symbolic structure.
I think there is a question
whether at large scale,
for example, this might go away.
I think to me, at least
a very subjective opinion
is it's still inefficient.
So in the sense that
even if we do OCR,
there will be how you choose
the appearance of the text.
How do you model the paragraph?
So there might be
certain inefficiency
with a-- we overlook
in this representation.
So I think one argument
OCR could be faster
is I think OCR input would allow
us to actually use a shorter
context to represent more text.
Because we can take a
screenshot of a paragraph,
and then we can just take
pictures for that paragraph,
versus we tokenize
the entire paragraph.
So I think there is some
argument about that.
I think it's interesting
and someone probably
should do that experiment.
So the reason why I was
wondering is because you--
right now, they don't know
that, for example, the text
is highlight or italic and
you have to add these markdown
tags to it.
And now they will just
naturally understand that.
And you mentioned
these infographics.
It seems like they'll
just unify pretty well.
And more from an
engineering perspective,
I was wondering if you
fuse these modalities,
you end up having a much
easier time training that.
Because you only need
audio and picture left.
And then all the downstream
mixture of expert stuff
will get easier and the
training will stabilize.
Probably easier, too.
Less babysitting.
So it seems obviously
inefficient.
But on a larger scale, on
a training dynamic scale,
it seems like it could be much
more efficient because of that.
Yeah.
I feel like someone
should study this.
The only thing is I feel like
at least from what we so far we
learn, if we want to unify these
modalities during training,
it's actually better
to align other things
onto text versus having
text aligned to the others.
Because I think
text, you already
drive these underlining
reasoning agentic capabilities.
For example, if we represent
texts as OCR, for example,
it might just makes scaling to
these capabilities much slower.
Oh.
How do you make image
into text modality?
So this is by the
tokenization I just mentioned.
So we just divide
them into patches.
Oh, that's what I was
proposing earlier.
You turn the text into
these image patches token,
and then do the regular
auto regression on it.
Yes.
Yeah, not a diffusion
process wholesale, but just
auto regression on
the image patches
that happen to
contain text stuff.
Again, never tried it myself.
So it's probably worth
try some experiments.
But I feel like predicting
clean symbolic symbols
versus this imageified text,
I think the former might
be more efficient.
Yeah, thank you.
Any other in-person questions?
All right, there's
some from online.
Yeah, someone
asked, could it help
to develop higher level, more
object oriented embeddings
for visual elements?
So infants or
humans, we naturally
understand pieces moving
together as one thing.
Yes.
I think I believe so.
I believe this is also the
research theme of Japa as well.
So basically having more
semantic representation
of the visual scenes.
I definitely think it's a
very interesting direction.
I think people
should explore, yeah.
I think the other questions
are somewhat related as well.
One of them is
asking, is it feasible
for a single representation to
capture enough for perception,
generation and reasoning,
or are separate hierarchies
likely needed?
Similar to how humans
process or think.
Yeah.
So I think there has already
been research started.
I think there are papers
published this year.
Super apology, I forgot
the title of the paper,
but it's from [INAUDIBLE] group.
So I think basically,
it's investigating,
can we unify the representation
for image generation
and understanding?
I think people are
seeing promising results.
So for example,
in the sense there
has already been
experimental results
showing even if you take
standard image encoding
representation, using that
for generation, people
are able to generate
good images out of it,
sometimes even outperform
like the VAE representation.
So I think philosophically, if
this direction got figured out,
basically that will push image
modeling closer to language
modeling one step further.
Because for language
model, we are
able to have this unified
text input and output.
So I feel philosophically,
this path makes sense.
And the field is
also making progress.
I have a question
that's subjective.
Do you think we should be
trying to make everything
like large language
models, auto regression?
Because I've talked to some
folks, including Andre,
and we have mixed feelings
about next token prediction.
From a cognitive standpoint
or at least the way
I think about it,
I feel like humans
learn in more structured,
hierarchical manners,
not simply predicting
the next token
given all the previous ones.
That's more of a
statistical learning
procedure, which works
well with LLMs, because you
have so much data.
So you're able to estimate
this distribution effectively.
But I feel fundamentally,
this is controversial,
but I feel like auto regression
is flawed or it works well.
It works surprisingly
and impressively well.
But I feel like we
need something more.
I feel like just the next
token prediction might not
be the move.
But I'm not sure if
you have any thoughts.
Yeah.
So I think the thought
is very interesting.
So I think there are people
trying different things,
like diffusion language models.
Discrete diffusion
language models.
Different ways, like compared
to next token prediction.
I personally think next
prediction has proved-- sorry,
next token prediction has proven
itself to be very effective.
And I think the catch
is even on the surface,
it's doing next
token prediction.
Because the network connection
is pretty complicated.
So there could already be in
structure learning emerged,
like in the latent space.
Which we don't understand well.
But it could be that next token
prediction is the surface form.
The network is doing
more than that.
No, I think that
makes a lot of sense.
Yeah.
I feel like because of how the
transformer and attention works,
I think you're
right, that there's
a lot of abstractions
or structure
that's being learned
that's hidden.
And next token
prediction, like you said,
might be the surface
way that that's--
at least it appears
like that's--
well, that's the way it
learns, the training objective.
But it's actually
learning more than that.
Yeah.
Any other questions, or--
Thanks for the presentation.
So what is your take on
the state of the art when
it comes to spatial reasoning?
So physical environments and
modality or multimodal models?
Yeah.
I'm not an expert in the
area of spatial reasoning,
so I think in terms of
the state of the art,
so I think we're seeing lots
of progress in robotics,
in robotics labs.
These vision language
action models.
So I think one
interesting observation
is I think some
of these, actually
they are being accelerated by
multimodal language models.
So for example, even for
the models coming out
from physical intelligence, they
leverage vision language models
as a backbone rather than
training from scratch.
So it seems like there are some
interesting positive transfer
from multimodal
language modeling
to spatial understanding.
So I think, on the
other hand, there
are definitely more labs, which
is taking more unique approach.
So but I'm less familiar
with those approach.
But I think I'm aware of
some approaches, which
is shifted more further away
from leveraging languages.
But having the
model less language
dependent, but focus more
on the visual signal.
But I'm not too familiar
with those approaches.
Yeah.
Sorry, I have one more question.
It's regarding what you
said about reasoning being
done much more effectively
in text space rather
than video space.
And how much of it is
a video data problem
rather than a pure
problem of visual video.
Because there's no good video
data where the person pauses
a bit and then he
monologues a bit and then
you hear the sound of it
or something like that.
Whereas in text, most texts are
full of reasoning and monologue
and pauses and all
these kind of stuff.
So in theory, if you train a
video model and intersperse
with frames of text or something
like that and this reasoning
problem seems to be
solved, like you said,
it will be either audio, which
is an approximation of the text,
or the text itself.
So I guess what I'm trying to
ask is, in what part of this
don't we already have a proof
that when you want reasoning,
you have to go down
to text anyway?
Right, OK.
So OK, I think the
question, to repeat
the question is, the question
is, it seems like you can only
synthetically augment
video through text,
through text in the video,
or text in the, I don't know,
the MP4 frame or text into
audio into that channel.
It seems like that's the
only thing we can do.
And if so, that's
much stronger proof
that we have to do synthetic
data with video interspersed
with text in various formats.
And that nothing else
will work as well.
OK, so I think basically, this
assumption is building on,
we have to reason with
language as a backbone.
So I think that has been
shown to be very effective.
And I agree.
Actually, synthetic data
is nowadays, very important
for vision tasks.
So it's always very important.
But I think that doesn't
rule out the possibilities
that we can still have pure
vision models that can reason.
So suppose nowadays,
if we have very good,
let's say, video next frame
prediction and we just
prompted with just what's
happening in the video,
if it is able to get next
what's happening in the future
accurately, I would call
that a type of reasoning.
Right.
But the data would
be lacking for lots
of these video reasoning stuff.
Because it's hard to generate
that as opposed to text.
And the other thing is,
it's the same question.
Where in a textual chat app,
you can just slice out text
and, for example, you can slice
out the reasoning and everything
is fine.
Whereas for video generation,
we actually give it to the user
as it is for various reasons.
And we don't ever
get to pause and do
some special dedicated
video reasoning
frames that we strip away
with a post-processing pass
to the user.
And so every frame has
to just mean something.
It's like, you don't
get to reasoning
at all in the video space.
Purely as a UX concern, because
it's already slow enough
to generate, I guess.
Yes.
I think efficiency-wise,
that's true.
So I think I would agree.
So nowadays, if we use
language as a skeleton,
it will help visual
reasoning much more.
So I think that part, I agree.
But I think that's also
partly because language
compared to visual information
is much more abstract.
But I think in some
sense, nowadays,
we train the model to go back
and forth from visual signal
into this abstract space.
Because we train it on
captioning and other things.
I think this has
proven to be useful.
At least it's useful nowadays.
I think it could
be an open question
whether that's what we--
maybe at some point when
computer skill good enough,
we can do just reasoning,
just in pure visual space.
Yeah.
OK, awesome.
Thanks again, Victoria,
for the amazing talk.
Let's give another
round of applause.
[APPLAUSE]